[Music]
n
Hello everybody welcome back to the ask
Abhijit show I hope everyone's doing
great I welcome you wherever you are
east west north south inside India
outside of India
welcome uh it's been a couple of weeks
since we did this live we did the last
episode of this of this show and as
everyone is remarking a lot has changed
in the world a lot is happening so we're
going to hopefully deal with that
hopefully you ask questions that are
relevant to all of that I'm going to
take questions from the live chat and
let me see who all is there in the live
chat right now I can see dearon pachara
uh Cosmic gaming 7781 rudra Jeet pamel
nandi deep kajul Air Warriors anurag
sorab Singa curious RC gorov been a
while art the clown Amisha Mishra hello
criek xrj official vinit Sangle GOP s
netian aush Pand an Annabeth Jackson Sor
of sarar Manisha cardoo Sant bhattia
edit
shat rousi do I remember you I do
remember you yes Welcome Back Sir skull
bries SK himansu rajpurohit arpit
Agarwal Sally ramram M kabon Ben Alex
mapper feminist Slayer hello drumar DK
red viraj deshmuk Anu aru and aan Pavan
Kumar Singh Vin esman Sam Satish hello
hs10 Akash ba Mr macius Jalal gadada
trti patil present yes pranav Sharma
rudra Shashank Kosik Einstein who aush
Pand Sunil
C uh clash with pushkar and everybody
else so I'm going to stop that now and
please go ahead and ask your questions
let's take some questions a lot
happening in the world like you like
many of you have remarked okay let us
take this question by air
warriors uh the question okay two
questions here firstly has Russia
supplied readymade nuclear weapons or
its technology to Iran and my views on
the unexpected earthquake in Iran
secondly will Russia and China come in
Iran's defense if Israel attacks Iran
interesting questions very relevant to
what's happening the things that are
that have changed in the world in recent
days weeks so yes recently about a week
or so ago roughly give or take There Was
An Unexpected earthquake in Iran in a
part of of Iran a region of Iran that is
not prone to seismic excitement let's
say seismic
activity if you could go to the map okay
good we can crack out the map on the
very first question of today's episode
but let's take a look at the map so here
we have the map okay we are to come back
to the subcontinent area and go slightly
westwards and that's where we have Iran
and you can see in the north of the
country you have tan which is slightly
south of the Caspian Sea and in this
region more or less there's been an
earthquake now this region is not prone
to earthquakes seismic activity Etc and
yet this happened it was what was the
the
uh how much did it measure on the RoR
scale I think around four something 4
point something or maybe 5 point
something which is not very powerful of
an earthquake and not very small an
earthquake either so uh that's the kind
of thing that's happened now what else
apart from an earthquake can cause
seismic activity obviously an
underground nuclear
test and maybe Iran is sending a message
to its adversaries and also to its
friends perhaps you so uh look those of
you who are regular Watchers of this
show know that I have said several times
in the past few months that I believe
Iran would probably already have a few
nuclear weapons they have a pretty
mature um uranium enrichment program
they've been doing that for a very long
time couple of decades at least uranium
enrichment via centri
that process uranium hexafluoride which
is a gas so I am sure they have
sufficient file material for a handful
whatever that means of nuclear weapons
nuclear warheads
so I actually if you ask me today I
consider I believe that there are 10
nuclear powers in the world 10 nations
with nuclear weapons and I believe Iran
would be one of those so I'm pretty sure
Iran is a nuclear weapons Power by now I
mean they haven't officially announced
it but maybe that earthquake was a
signal to Nations like Israel and the US
and whoever else that listen don't don't
cross certain
lines uh and yeah so I don't believe
that Russia would have supplied nuclear
weapons or technology to Iran maybe some
kind of Aid in some indirect way perhaps
but I don't think Russia would actually
Supply nuclear weapons readymade weapons
to Iran maybe some kind of Aid in terms
of uh enrichment technology or something
but not not beyond that most likely of
course I could be wrong but look this is
all speculation we don't know what's
really happening and uh I appreciate
that you asked me whether Russia has
done this but I am not on talking terms
I mean I I I'm not privy to what Mr
Putin does and uh what happens there
right these are extremely secret matters
highly classified so can't can't comment
about that but I believe by now that but
that by now Iran is a nuclear weapons
power they most likely have a handful
whatever that means of nuclear Warriors
maybe 10 maybe 20 whatever it is and
they have a tremendous ballistic missile
and and cruise missile capabilities
right as they have demonstrated so and
and the last U attack that happened you
know the attack that uh Iran did on
Israel with with missiles with a whole
with about 200 missiles many of those
missiles hit the targets and
many of these missiles were extremely
high velocity missiles hypersonics like
they say right and um they seem to
maneuver as well so there was maneuver
maneuvering capability uh that these
missiles or or the WarHeads had the
explosions were rather small but that is
also something that sends a
message that these missiles can carry
small payloads that's that's enough for
a nuclear warhead so yeah that's how I
see it now the second question is will
Russia and China come in Iran's defense
if Israel attacks Iran I don't think so
not directly uh Russia will Aid Iran in
a variety of ways China will Aid Iran in
a variety of ways Russia may sell um a
high quality fighter planes to Iran
maybe that's that's already in the way
the Suk the latest sukko thing sukko 57
is
it and Iran already has excellent uh
cruise missile and ballistic missile
capability
uh but Russia and Iran has been
supplying Russia with those Shahed to
loitering Munitions drones and so on
there's a lot of synergy between the two
Nations even China has invested in Iran
it's it's invested big time in Iran uh
they've invested more than $400 billion
dollar worth of U resources in Iran over
a 25 year period That's a kind of
strategic deal they have so these
nations China and Russia are
significantly invested in Iran they need
Iran to keep existing and remain a
strong force in the West Asia region the
subcontinent plus region because that
that creates a certain kind of balance
of power in the region and they need
that so they will certainly Aid Iran in
a variety of ways but probably not
direct involvement right China is anyway
geographically too far away to be
directly involved in in any conflict
that involves Iran Russia is nearby
let's go back to the m map and I'll show
you how it is so how is Russia nearby
when it comes to Iran uh excuse
me so if you go north of Iran you have
the Caspian Sea and well to the West in
the western part of the Caspian Sea you
already have the Caucasus region uh the
cities of uh you know the cities of ch
ch dagistan Etc and so on so Russia is
right there Russia is very much in the
neighborhood so Russia could get
involved directly if it so
desires uh but one one hopes that it
doesn't come to all that one hopes that
there isn't a war because war is is
terrible for everybody concerned
including Nations that aren't involved
directly in the war like India you know
if there's a war in the region you're
going to see oil prices shooting up and
that's bad for our economy so there we
have it so that's that's kind of the
question the answer to your questions
good question and let's see what else is
going
on cile takes us in a whole different
direction why was how was was you say
Bol so fast compared to other top
sprinters could be just genetics which
made him the best can his 100 meter
world record ever be broken look a lot
has to do with genetics most people
simply can't imagine running at anything
close to that
speed uh that us Bol bolt was able to
accomplish and of course Yen bolt
trained incredibly
hard tremendously hard training
tremendous work ethic I've seen some of
his training videos I mean you know the
things that he put himself through to
get into that shape uh not easy if you
if you're a lifter in gym and you know
what leg day is then you know that if
you really push hard in your leg on leg
day your stomach is going to give away
and you're going to have to throw up in
a bucket right usen bold used to throw
up regularly because every day was leg
day for him right legs sprinting and
whatnot my goodness the the the work
ethic was incredible and obviously work
ethic you may have the greatest work
ethic but without genetics you w be able
to reach the 1% of the 1% of the 1% so I
think it's something to do with
tremendous genetics plus an incredible
work ethic that the combination of those
two is what made him the greatest that
we have ever seen thus far will his
world record ever be broken probably
someday it will be broken probably
someday we will disc discover somebody
with even better
genetics I remember when
when I was a little kid uh 1988 Olympics
Soul uh the Canadian Sprinter Ben
Johnson set a world record the next day
he was caught doping and his he was
stripped of his medals the world record
was erased but I thought that it was at
I think it was 9.86 or something I
thought nobody can break that as a kid
you know he you're really
naive But Here we are now it's what
what's the world record currently 9.5
something well you can see how how much
of a change change there's been so I
think it will eventually be broken but
only a new Legend can break that record
I would say so
yeah
okay Dr aul says does Dentistry have
good opportunity in India is it better
to work abroad than to set up a clinic
in India well look we have a we have the
world's largest population our dietary
habits are changing Indians eat a lot of
junk food these days Indians have
adopted the the American kind of diet
which causes a tremendous amount of
dental problems cavities carries Dental
carries and whatnot so I think there's
always going to be a market for d for
for a huge U target audience let's say
for dentists in India you're going to
see that I mean especially kids I mean
their dental hygiene habits aren't that
good anymore the kind of stuff they eat
so I I think look Dentistry so it's very
clear that Dentistry if you're a dentist
you're going to always have good
opportunities you're going to always
have customers in India the question is
is can you uh make the kind of money in
India as a dentist as you could do let's
say in the west somewhere or or in any
first world country probably not uh so
if you're a really good dentist highly
skilled maybe it makes sense if you want
to get rich who doesn't to perhaps go
abroad I always tell people if you have
the opportunity to go abroad and get get
wealthy please do so no no question
about it so yeah uh Dentistry you you
will always you will never be unemployed
as a dentist in India you you will
always have clients as long as you
competent right but you want get as rich
in India doing the same work as you
could get if you were let's say in a
western country or a first world country
and that's the long and the short of the
answer
okay shahu says uh thank you recently
the Israelis did a Cyber attack on Iran
and also the internet archive website
was act I heard about that yes how
should India be prepared for cyber
warfare we should have adequate
offensive as well as defensive
capabilities right that's that's what
that's how India should prepare uh and
it's not something you can develop
overnight let's say you're a nation that
doesn't have any capability in this
particular domain cyber warfare well
it's going to take you first of all
you're going to have to identify a whole
bunch of t talented programmers and uh
penetration
uh hacking experts and you know the
whole whole gamut you know you're going
to have to identify a bunch of people
you're going to have to test
them especially you would want to
identify young kids young kids as in
teenagers and college students who are
really good at this you know it takes
time to develop the capabilities it may
take you at least 5 to 10 years to get
decent at
this so uh look we we don't know what
India's cyber warfare capabilities are
we don't speak about that obviously if
you have capabilities you will not you
will not advertise those uh I am pretty
sure India is re reasonably well
equipped when it comes to these
capabilities I think India is one of the
top nations in in when it comes to cyber
warfare capabilities offense as well as
defense so how should India prepare for
this India should be aware of the
current threat scenario what are the
current threats what are the current
attacks that are happening wherever in
the world who is conducting the these
attacks you should know who's doing that
what are the techniques they're using
what uh how how are they doing it you
got to always stay ahead of the
curve um and yeah it's just like any War
you
can't sometimes you get hit no matter
how good you are so you've got to
develop these capabilities and keep on
improving them and you to hi hire the
hire the best identify and hire the best
talent so I think India hopefully is
doing this okay we haven't advertised
any of that which we obviously
shouldn't uh but yes the Israel has did
a Cyber attack on Iran and it's very
surprising the internet archive website
has been hacked I'm not sure if it's
still on right is it back on i' would be
very disappointed if it goes down it's a
it's a great resource and I don't
understand why that website needs to be
targeted by Whoever has done that but
well such is the world so I think India
is reasonably I I I believe India is
pretty well equipped when it comes to
cyber warfare capabilities and obviously
they will know how to handle this better
than
us
okay okay feminist Slayer says I was
showing slight aggression in pursuing my
goals I didn't harm anyone but a girl in
my study group accused me of showing
toxic masculinity masculinity isn't
assertiveness a natur natural trait in
guys you see this this entire feminist
uh thing feminist worldview feminist
ideology is is now um making its way
into India it's been doing so for the
past at least two decades and now just
being who you are as as a male is seen
as toxic masculinity look if there's a
girl in your study group is accusing you
of doing this I think you need to change
study groups that's what I would say and
I would request our our female Brethren
Brethren sister and whatever it is
look I mean males are males as long as
someone's someone's not being aggressive
towards you just leave them alone
right uh anyway that's that's something
we're going to be dealing with of
in increasingly in the coming years
because look the world's most powerful
Nation the world's most influential
Nation the world's world's most
important the United States is exporting
all of this
so there's nothing we can do about it
unless you you create
a a fire wall like the Chinese have
right and you don't want to be isolated
from the rest of the world right the
Chinese have done a pretty good job of
of
selectively uh allowing their citizens
to access websites and all that but well
probably India is not is way is not
capable of doing that or won't even want
to do that so my my point is look if if
someone's behaving in this manner
towards you accusing you you of of of
tox toxic masculinity I think there's no
point fighting with such people you need
to change your study group and find
better people okay that's what I would
say
Okay rtic pungle says have I read any
religious books I have read plenty of
religious books I have mostly to most
mostly books that deal with my religion
but also curiously I've been curious
enough to uh Venture Beyond My Religion
and just to get a sense of what the
others are talking about see yes I have
read religious books I
have mlin says India and the US have
signed a deal to manufacture
semiconductor fabrication plant is it
safe to join hands with the US in such
an important
industry
uh it's a good question
sir
U uh ideally you want to go It
Alone ideally want you should do it on
your own it'll take you 20 years perhaps
to reach where you want to reach but so
what so what uh for some reason there's
a significant amount of
closeness between India and the US
nothing I have nothing against the us
but we know that the US sees India as a
long-term threat and arrival longterm
not today today India is insignificant
today India is like a grasshopper on the
grass okay in 20 years India could be
the next China if India continues along
the same trajectory that it's on right
now by by 2050 Horizon India could be a
genuine competitor for the US so the US
doesn't want that to happen so India has
you know India is greatly penetrated
let's say by the us and this penetration
began in the early '90s after the after
the Downing of of the Iron Curtain and
that's when Indian politicians needed
new daddies and that's where the
infiltration of India began as
especially after the the economic
reforms of the early
90s um and so on so India is deeply
penetrated uh the superpower has assets
all over the place within India in every
institution in every political party one
would
imagine uh so it's not that surprising
that the Americans uh
are are involved in all these things I
think it kind of to some extent
compromises the country yeah but yeah
that that that's where you are today I
mean you
have I remember Google provides
Wi-Fi to Indians in various Railway
stations in India we've allowed Google
to do that free Wi-Fi I mean if you want
to save a little a few bucks just to
save a few bucks you you
inviting Google to provide Wi-Fi they're
going to collect all the information all
the data of every single person who
passes through the Rel station but there
you have it so I think we we have
these rather bizarre
policies uh the government I think
clearly the people who run the
government are way more intelligent than
somebody like me so probably they know
better but I think it's rather one has
to be more careful than what we being
right
now okay Samar says how do I send a
question to to abijit sir sir you just
sent a question I took it this is how
you send questions if you have a
question in your mind you just put it up
over here in the live chat and if I I I
happen to see it I'll pick it up if it's
interesting enough so please ask good
questions aayush Pand says my views on
the recent Starship launch do I consider
it successful or partially successful
this happened a couple of hours ago two
three hours ago the Starship is the most
powerful uh rocket
ever built it's more powerful than the
Saturn 5 rocket that was built by
uh what's his name I forget the name um
not wner Heisenberg but but Verner Von
Brown the German rocket scientist who
later became American so he built the uh
s five rocket in the 1960s the rocket
that took the first humans to the moon
to the moon's surface and brought them
back oh the rocket didn't bring them
back but at the point now the Starship
that Elon Musk is building is developing
currently SpaceX with SpaceX and which
is his company Starship is the most
powerful rocket Humanity has ever built
and the latest launch happened just like
two three hours before right this moment
so the rocket took off uh and I haven't
seen the details of the of the whether
it went into orbit or not I know that
the uh rocket took off successfully
uh I know that uh probably the rocket
itself touched
down on U on one of those ships you know
at Sea and it it touched down
successfully it's not been lost it's not
been destroyed it touched down and it's
going to be brought back to the
facilities and the booster also came
back and it was actually captured by the
that gigantic clamp on that Launchpad so
the booster also came back and in a very
precise way it was captured by by the
two clamps so it's an incredible success
it's it's not partially successful it's
successful beyond your viess
imagination so I think Starship is
almost
ready I'm sure they're going to test it
a couple more times before sending it on
an official
mission but there we have it I mean it's
it's it's incredible progress that
SpaceX is doing in
2017 you had the first rudimentary
Starship that was that was tested by by
Space X it was a very very make
makeshift kind of
contraption and in just seven years
they've they've successfully achieved
what they achieve today it's incredible
the pace at which the progress and
development is happening is incredible
compare that with
ISRO what has changed in ISRO in the
past past seven years almost nothing a
little bit you may have what the
whatever the new rocket is called uh
slightly more powerful than the one we
had earlier I mean it's it's incremental
progress we are doing in ISRO I'm not
blaming the scientists at is the
engineers in is I'm not blam blaming the
head of
is they can only do what they're allowed
to do what they ordered to
do but there's no ambition why aren't we
developing reusable rocket technology
why are we why aren't we thinking out of
the box and doing something even SpaceX
hasn't thought of why aren't we doing
something different we just following
following copying copying in a small way
with a tiny budget how many launches
does ISRO do every year what four
five it's it's uh it's simply staggering
the lack of ambition our leaders have uh
in in this in the field of science and
other fields as well so I think the US
is now way ahead of the rest of the
world what SpaceX is achieving is
Monumental I would like to congratulate
Elon Musk officially Elon if you're
watching
congratulations you're doing
tremendously well and and in a few years
probably by the by 2030 or maybe by 2035
you're going to have humans on the on on
mass I think in two three years whenever
the next launch window opens up you have
a launch video every I don't know 20 six
months or something if you can look it
up for
M every every few months 26 or whatever
months you have a launch window that
opens up for sending a spacecraft to
mass which is the optimum amount of
travel that you do least amount of
travel in the shortest amount of time so
whenever that opens up next I'm sure
they're going to send a couple of at
least one one Starship to Mars as a test
mission and I think in a few years
you're going to have the first human
that will be sent toor so I think it's
tremendous progress that's happening and
SpaceX is showing the world what can be
done so yeah great to see that and sad
that we have nobody with even 1% of that
ambition in India and if people have
ambition they they aren't the ones with
the money so that's where we
are buit Joi says how does Iran getting
nukes affect India those nukes aren't
for India but it's always interesting to
have a new nuclear weapons power in the
neighborhood so let's take a look at the
map uh here is the map should I make it
yeah this is better way of looking at it
so here's our neighborhood the
subcontinent plus region yes and we
have I mean we have India a nuclear
weapons power uh north and east of us we
have China new nuclear weapons power
west of us we have a temporary nation
that is temporarily a nuclear weapons
power in west of Pakistan we have what
is probably another newly minted nuclear
weapons power Iran this neighborhood wow
just imagine that four nuclear powers in
the region and if you go eastwards we
have North Korea another nuclear weapons
power and so
on now the nukes that Iran is developing
aren't meant for IND
they are meant for for
um ensuring Iran's uh defense visavi
Israel Iran considers Israel to be its
number one enemy apart
from like they say the United States um
and having nuclear weapons ensures a
significant amount of it is a deterrent
isn't it any Nation would think twice
Thrice 100 times before attacking a
nation that has nuclear weapons and the
ability to deliver the nuclear weapons
and Iran certainly has the ability to
deliver nuclear weapons it has excellent
missiles as theyve demonstrated multiple
times so it kind of changes the balance
of power in the region Iran becomes a
different kind of entity now its hard
power score
changes increases not decreases it has
an effect on Pakistan Pakistan is nucle
nuclear weapons power they always say
that we are the Islamic we have the
Islamic bomb we the only Islamic Nation
to have a nuclear weapons program well
that no longer works now Iran too has
that so Pakistan also can't can't bully
Iran I mean they've never tried
significantly bullying Iran but Iran and
Pakistan aren't ever the best of friends
unless you go go back to the 1960s which
was a different story so they're kind of
geopolitical Rivals Iran in Pakistan not
on the best of terms ever so now that
introduces a whole different dimension
in that relationship bilateral
relationship Iran Pakistan but overall
it it u
means that the Iran Israel Dynamic
changes a lot now Israel will be will
have to be really careful it can't uh if
it if if Israel had harbard hopes of
let's say uh destroying Iran
capabilities military capabilities
through a barrage of missile strikes or
air strikes and all now that is a little
they have to think a 100 times before
they do that and so on so the whole
relationship has changed the whole
dynamic has changed Iran has
demonstrated that it can rain down
missiles and strike targets within
Israel despite Israel having the iron
doome system A lot changes for India I
don't think a lot changes VAV Iran we
don't have any any overall problems with
Iran we are working together with Iran
in in a variety of ways the chabahar
project is a great example of that so
overall we are kind of on good terms
India and Iran of course the American
sanctions have kind of strained the
relationship Iran would have wanted
India to buy a lot of oil from them
because they're right next door why
should we not but the Americans have
kind of prevented India from doing that
and that's kind of the the US Factor has
kind of strained the relationship
between India and Iran to some extent
but we aren't rivals in any any shape or
form whatsoever so Iran getting nukes it
changes the balance of power in the
region to a certain extent it makes Iran
harder to destroy if you are an
adversary of Iran for
India what does it mean it ises well it
doesn't set off any alarm bells in India
for sure not at all of course we will
now have to calculate things differently
when it comes to the region uh but
overall it it's uh not a bad thing um as
as far as we in India are concerned
excuse me I've got a
old uh but yeah it's something we have
to think about it's certainly something
we to think about it changes the balance
of power the Dynamics in the region it
it complicates matters in our
neighborhood for sure but it's not a
threat for India but we still have to
look at it differently it's complicated
matter complicated definitely
okay okay Nan panal says which is the
most dangerous security threat at the
Red Sea the hutis or the Somali pirates
describe in the detail okay so let's see
where the Red Sea is the Red Sea it
connects well it's it's this stretch of
ocean that exists between the the
Arabian Peninsula and Africa it it
begins when where the Gulf of Adan ends
at the straight of bab
almand and it it terminates in Su Al Su
or whatever yeah El which which is where
the Su Canal begins which connects the
Red Sea to the Mediterranean Sea now the
question is which is the most dangerous
security threat in this overall region
so of course we have jibuti which is at
the at the commencement let's say of the
Red Sea and east of jibuti we have
Somalia right and Somalia is a nation
that is Strife torn uh very little
governance exists there and you have
these uh Pirates Warlords and pirates
that run the roost in Somalia sadly
which is a a tragedy for the nation but
it is what it is and I'll not go into
the historical roots of that particular
situation so one threat for shipping is
the Somali
pirates and they these Somali pirates
aren't Hightech Pirates they don't have
the best technology they usually have
AK-47s and um grenade launchers rocket
launchers that sort of thing reasonably
rudimentary technology they have speed
bools and so on and they they have
numbers and they have been terrorizing
shipping in the region for for quite
quite a while quite a number of years
right and then you have the houis the an
Allah faction in Yemen uh which is an
anti-west uh faction well can't blame
them for what they are they have been
targeted by the West for so long a war
essentially has been raging in Yemen
since the 1960s
70s and Yemen has been devastated by
that and one well can one
blame the people of Yemen for trying to
fight that so anyway if you want to
understand the Yemen situation there is
a video podcast on this channel it's
with Dr Isa blumi in which he speaks
about in which he goes into this matter
in great detail if you are interested
you can check out that particular
podcast it's from a couple of years ago
roughly so there you have that now the
huis they are allies of Iran and they
have access to certain Iranian
Technologies they seem to have cruise
missiles and ballistic missiles
well that makes the houis way more
dangerous if you are their
enemy than the Somali pirates the Somali
pirates don't have any such advanced
technology they don't have missiles they
have rocket rocket launchers launchers
at best so that's why I I would say I
hope I'm able to justify this that I'm
sure you understand that AK-47s and
rocket launchers and grenade launchers
on one side on the other side you have
ballistic missiles and cruise missiles
this is a way more dangerous technology
so the houis are more dangerous more
dangerous security threat if you are an
adversary if you are India they will not
bother you because we aren't their enemy
but yeah the huis are way more powerful
than the Somali
pirates
okay um
let's see what
else ala says will India have Sinn than
Punjab look that's the same old question
isn't it when does it's about P it's
about Pakistan and so on be patient look
we we are a 10,000 year old civilization
at least few years here and there what's
the big deal we will have it back right
what the question is do we want those
people along with the package along with
the land the land is ours obviously it's
being it's our ancestral land is our
sacred land so in the Punjab all of that
even Gandhara would say uh
bistan Etc but uh it will eventually
happen look Pakistan is an artificial
Nation it's a temporary Nation it is
propped up by foreign powers who uh and
and the the utility that Pakistan has
for them is that it serves a certain
geopolitical agenda counterbalancing
India of being a nuisance for
India and so on so that's why they need
Pakistan over there
as long as this need exists Pakistan
will be made to exist it will be propped
up and they'll ensure that nothing
happens when they no longer need
Pakistan whenever that happens Pakistan
will spontaneously disintegrate then the
question is do we want to have uh the
rest of Punjab back within India and do
we want Sy back in India the problem is
the population is extremely highly
radicalized and they hate us they are
the same blood as us they have the same
ancestors as us they are our people but
they hate us okay religious factors or
whatever factors I don't don't to go
into the detail I think we all
understand that do we want that
population do we want to have them
within our
borders can we live with those people is
the question most of them hate us right
so I think it's going to take
time eventually the subcontinent will
reunify eventually but that may take a
100 years maybe it's a 100-year project
it's not going to
happen even if it's available tomorrow
do you want them those people within
your borders that's the question you to
ask yourself I would say no so not yet
so I would say that eventually whenever
it happens Pakistan will fragment it
will break up uh po that'll return to
India because that doesn't make too much
of a difference anyway right now
considering the
situation in that region kak goes back
to Afghanistan it gandhar becomes it
merges with with with Afghanistan
baluchistan probably becomes
independent Sy probably becomes
independent and uh punjabian or whatever
it is becomes independent and that
situation will persist for a few decades
perhaps and hopefully at some point in
time if the population becomes
deradicalized and they stop hating their
own people then maybe we can reabsorb
them within the fold of Indian
civilization but of course right now we
are just a nation we're not a
civilization officially right so it's I
think it's a long story it's going to be
a long project maybe a 100 years project
maybe a 150e project but for us what's
the What's 100
years for us 100 years is nothing it's
it's like a weekend so be patient be
patient
friends
uh uh aush Pand says do you consider the
attack of Iran with fat to missile of
Mac 15 speed a joke I mean with one ton
payload it would have kinetic energy
equivalent to three tons of
TNT look if you are impacting at Mark 15
15 times the speed of
sound look consider the brahmos the
brahmos is a is a Mac 2 missile right
and even if you don't put a payload a
warhead on the brahmos even if it it's
not equipped with a warhead if it
impacts a ship it's going to just cut
the ship in ship in half just because of
his kinetic energy that's how dangerous
the brahos is at Mac 2 now if you have a
missile that's a
Hypersonic um a Hypersonic is Mac 5 plus
right uh that's typically a cruise
missile but when you talk about ma 15
you're talking about close to re-entry
speeds that's ballistic missiles
ballistic missiles they re-enter the
atmosphere at about Mac 20 plus around
around Mac 20 and there may impact
around Mac 15 or or whatever it is maybe
even higher than mac
15 it's once you are within the
atmosphere your missile is within the
atmosphere you got a I don't know bunch
of
seconds how much time do you have before
you can even think of intercepting the
missile so Mac 15 is not a joke I mean
why why would you consider that to be a
joke that missile will cause Devastation
even without a payload any you don't
need a one turn payload you can have a
kilo uh conventional payload it will
cause a lot of damage I think the
payloads they they sent on those
missiles the Iranians those the latest
attack those seem to be small payload
because the the because the explosions
were rather small but maybe they were
trying to send a different kind of
message um so yeah in case you've done
the the calculation of kinetic energy
and all I'm not sure three tons of TNT
is it's decent I don't think it's a joke
B
uh they could have sent larger payloads
on those missiles maybe it would have
changed the velocity profile Etc of the
missiles and maybe they would it would
have made those missiles slightly easier
slightly easier to intercept and maybe
they wanted to send a certain message
that's why they did it but it's clearly
not a joke this is not a joke when you
have a when you have ballistic missile
incoming at at re-entry speeds roughly
in the region of Mark 20 that is not a
joke
so
yeah
okay uh bries SK says if Israel destroys
nuclear facilities which are the
countries which will get affected by
radiation look
uh I'm I'm assuming you're talking about
Iran's nuclear
facilities if Israel successfully let's
say in know hypothetical scenario where
to target Iran's nuclear facilities and
let's say like you're saying it destroys
those facilities what's going to happen
you're going to have explosions right
they'll be targeted through air strikes
or missiles or or sabotage three three
possible scenarios one can uh
inage now uh when you have explosions
and you have nuclear materials nuclear
fuel Etc and you have an explosion
that's going to get uh vaporized to some
extent it's going to go out in the
atmosphere so depending on the amount of
nuclear uh material that is released in
the
atmosphere
and how high it is released and the wind
and climate situation you could have you
could have different outcomes so I
remember when CH Chernobyl happened when
I was a kid I was in Europe at the time
there was this cloud of radio
Radioactive uh fallout that was hovering
over Europe and we kids were told not to
go and play football in the grass
because you could have radiation
contamination over there so that
situation persisted for a couple of
months or something uh now in the case
of Chernobyl it was a big explosion and
a tremendous amount of nuclear uh
fallout nuclear material was ped into
the atmosphere that's a nuclear reactor
which is which naturally operates at
extremely high temperatures and
pressures and there was a melt down in
that now if you target nuclear
facilities where you have stored fuel
you won't have that sort of situation
you will have some Fallout into the
atmosphere but not to that extent so a
it's it's an interesting question from a
theoretical perspective I don't think
the uh fallout will be very great
obviously it's going to cause some
problems but it
won't
uh Chernobyl was like a nuclear blast
almost and it went High into the
atmosphere in the case of something like
this it won't probably go very high in
atmosphere so most likely the host
country will be the one that's affected
the most and even in that case it may
not be a very widespread
area uh so that's what I would imagine
it would be like I not actually run the
scenarios through proper calculations or
anything but uh most likely it won't
spread far and wide if look we talking
about Iran here I mean I'm I'm not
saying this should happen okay but if it
happens uh probably it will be contained
within Iran and the neighboring Nations
uh what are the wind patterns like I'm
not sure so I don't think it'll go go
very far as far as I'm as far as I
can see without doing any actual
calculations Shri har ner says I might
have a chance to get into tsmc Taiwan
semiconductor Corporation right
Manufacturing corporation uh as machine
learning engineer in Taiwan how safe is
it to relocate there for the next two
three years well that's always
um I think it should be pretty safe next
two three years I don't think China is
going to try anything
stupid I don't think China will try and
grab Taiwan okay look I could be wrong
okay I could be wrong I am not some
fortune teller I cannot see the future I
can only weigh
probabilities I deal with probabilities
I think the probability of China
invading Taiwan and all that happening
is pretty low right
now uh in the ideal scenario from
China's perspective they walk into
Taiwan without any Warfare they get
Taiwan untouched not not a broken shell
of a
country so I think it should be pretty
safe I don't think we are in that
scenario because if if China makes a
move on Taiwan it's it's very close to
World War II because the US will
immediately get involved and there's
going to be a lot of fighting and all
that uh if you have the chance to be
there two three years I think you should
go ahead for
it and uh even if there's a war that
breaks out they will not want to touch
civilians or or
uh or do anything that harms civilians
it makes them look bad so overall I
don't think it's uh something you should
worry about too much if you get if you
get an opportunity go grab
it but I say this with the caveat look
I'm not a fortune teller okay but uh
even if a war happens like I said they
probably want they definitely do not
want to touch civilians so overall you
would be safe and the Taiwan have the
bunkers and all that in case of War
happens so anyway hopefully civilians
will anyway be safe so I think if you
get the chance don't waste it go for it
okay hs10 says what is hawking radiation
okay we're going from geopolitics into
theoretical physics and this is
theoretical physics we have never
observed this but let me explain what it
is hawking radiation let me tell you
very briefly is something to do with
black holes black holes are we think of
black holes as giant vacuum cleaners
right that's the popular depiction of
black Hol it's is this big black thing
that stucks everything in and once you
you fall into it you can never come back
Etc so that's what you typically think
of black holes that exist in Far Away
space but black holes they actually have
a temperature black holes aren't all
they don't just suck everything in they
even radiate so that is walking
radiation um and the larger a black hole
the cooler it is and the slower is the
the the lesser amount of particles it
emits and the smaller a black hole is
the hotter it is and the more it radi
rates so Hawking radiation is is thermal
radiation that comes out of black holes
it is because of the temperature of a
black hole any object that has a
temperature it radiates something right
the sun has a certain temperature it
radiates so much radiation light heat
and and solar wind and all that
similarly black holes also radiate
something called Hawking radiation which
has if you understand what I'm talking
about it has a black body uh profile so
that's what Hawking radiation is it is
radiation given off by black holes
depending on their temperature the
smaller black hole is the more it
radiates the faster it radiates which
tells you that once a black hole reaches
a certain size it's just boom goes boom
and dies so that's Hawking radiation and
Hawking
evaporation tanay Chandra says excuse
me has Pakistan made a joke out of
itself by inviting Zaki nyak as the
state guest and have you seen how he Ro
roast Pakistan uh okay I haven't seen
what has been going on Visa that person
I don't find the person interesting I
don't find Pakistan overall as a nation
or a society interesting my apologies to
any pakistanis who may be watching I
simply don't find it interesting okay um
and yeah I'm aware that the that that
the the person has been invited to
Pakistan he visited and I heard that he
did not he kind
of some people are think he made a fool
of himself so uh I don't know the
details I haven't been watching the
videos or anything but I heard something
to this effect and he roasted Pakistan
well I don't I'm not aware of that why
would you roast your own hosts that is
rather stupid so I'm not aware it's not
something I like to follow the these
things you know I'm sure there are lots
of YouTubers who follow this sort of
thing lots of channels who who make
their whole content about around these
matters it's not something that
interests me so anyway Pakistan zakin n
whatever
topics that aren't quite for
me okay aush Pand says why does Russia
need missiles like
BN with ballistic missiles like Satan 2
and avangard you need a whole variety of
missiles as a nation for for example we
in India have the brahmas and we working
on the brahmas too why don't we have a
whole different kind of Miss family of
missiles wait we do don't we we have a
whole assortment of missiles some are
ballistic missiles some are short range
ballistic missiles medium range long
range hyper long long range perhaps
ballistic missiles we have mirv equipped
missiles we have cruise missiles we have
subsonic cruise missiles we have
supersonic cruise missiles we may be
working on something another other Sonic
cruise missile we have cruise missiles
that deploy
Torpedoes we have all kinds of things
you need a whole assortment of different
kinds of Misses for different kinds of
scenarios just because you have a very
super powerful big missile doesn't mean
that you should not develop anything
else the Satan 2 is an intercontinental
ballistic missile it's extremely large
and uh it is it can I don't know deploy
at least 10 Warheads MV equipped MV MV
equipped
Warheads um they also have other
missiles they have the kinal they have
the
siron um and so on so you're always
developing you're always trying to
improve upon what you have that is the
mark of a nation that takes itself
successfully you don't just develop a
and then sit down and relax okay C done
happy now you keep on uh developing new
things you have to be a little paranoid
when it comes to when it comes to the
the domain of geopolitics especially if
you are a major power so that's why
Russia does it it needs a variety of
missiles for a variety of different
scenarios and purposes it's like why why
do we need to uh develop other aircraft
when we have the thees they just mark
one mark two
whatever why don't we have strategic
bombers why don't we have flying wing
stealth aircraft why don't we have
stealth bombers why don't we have
unmanned fighter planes why don't we
have twin engine fighter planes why
don't we I mean I could go on same thing
applies to missiles so you should have
an assortment of different kinds of
missiles Ted x77 says will unemployment
problem ever end in India we don't have
very high rates of unemployment I think
the government has done a pretty good
job at uh at uh when it comes to
unemployment look in most parts of the
country uh I know that uh if you are a
graduate if you have a master's degree
or whatever if you have gone through
higher education it may be really hard
to get a job I I I am aware of that
situation but as long as you are willing
to do work you probably will get a job
of some
kind so I don't think we have much of an
unemployment prog problem in India the
problem is that people want salaries of
I want a salary of two lakhs per
month I I do I have an MBA or I have a
master's degree or I have a bachelor's
and a diploma and whatever and I believe
that I am worthy of having a salary of
so and so and I will not accept any job
which gives me a lower salary and then
you sit down and say I'm an employed
that attitude is a huge problem there's
this big attitude of entitlement that
lots of people have look we are a
developing country there are certain
constraints in the country you need to
be a a contributing member of society I
agree that you know the education system
is garbage and these degrees that you
get are not worth the paper they printed
on in a lot of cases that's true but
then what do you do with it you going to
sit home sit at home and do nothing and
uh depend on your parents to to to care
for you that's not how it should work
and it won't it's not sustainable
eventually you'll be on your own so I
think that that problem exists but
overall unemployment is not that big of
an issue in
India um and as India India's economy
grows I think uh more and more
opportunities will slowly gradually
start opening themselves up for people
with even with higher
education so that's how I see it I think
we should not complain too much okay uh
we are you you
know India's GDP per capita was about
2,500 it was about
$2,500 in
1947 you know what's India's GDP per
capita today it's $2,500 roughly roughly
the
same in between 1947 and 2024 India's
GDP per capita went below 800 thanks to
who I think you know thanks to who right
so we have just one once again attained
the position that we had in 1947 so it's
like we are we we have just attained
Independence now and now we start
working that's where we are okay so uh
if you are in that situation you're
going to have problems in the economy
it's going to take time to solve the
problems and I think the current
government has done a tremendous amount
of work in the past decade to alleviate
a lot of things so of course they have
every government has certain problems
and certain things they can improve upon
but overall they've done a great job
so I think we should not complain so
much we should find whatever
opportunities are available and do the
best we can with
that
okay okay what else oh okay mclen says
uh why did India never have hats even
though it's always been so sunny and hot
we had a
pagy but no head wear with a brim how
that's an interesting question I think
somebody who is into the field of
Sociology should take this up
interesting
question uh we had pag so what what is a
pag a turban do it not
only kind of keeps the Sun away it also
mops up your sweat because India is a
hot India has the past two and a half
thousand years 3,000 years had a
reasonably hot climate before that India
had a cooler climate in a heavier
Monsoon but in the past 3,000 years we
we've had a reasonably hot climate
um yeah it's it's a really interesting
question you ask how did how come we
never developed hats with brims we
always had puges that sort of headgear
and only males wear that ladies don't
wear that right I cannot think of any
ancient statue or carving of of of any
Indian person a female of a lady wearing
a pugy
right interesting very
interesting don't think I have the
answer to this question well that's not
often that it happens right so mavin has
asked a very interesting question
here and yeah I have to ponder about it
I I'm not able to give you an answer
right now how did that not evolve and to
understand to kind of go in the
direction of
understanding the issue and and and
trying to find an answer a plausible
answer to this question one has to go
into the history of hats so hats is
something you have in in Europe right
it's a Western concept hats hats with
brims what's the history of hats and
caps that's something you to go into to
understand how
that particular piece of attire emerged
in Western Society if you if you look at
uh Nations like Russia Etc they also
don't really have hats they used to have
these fur F caps that are like snug on
your head but they don't quite have
brims interesting question so yeah maybe
I'll do some research about this and get
back to you maybe in a future episode
interesting question you ask I really
appreciate
that
okay Canan says in pag is cheaper and
India is very price sensitive you see I
totally agree India prices matter a lot
in India people can't afford a lot of
money but historically we were the
world's largest economy so we see things
from the perspective of today maybe last
two decades three decades we see things
from the lens of post 1947 or post 18th
century post 19th century but we
understand India is a at least 10,000
year old civilization and before the
foreigners came and colonized India
India was incredibly prosperous and
prices didn't really matter that much in
those
days okay we were not living hand to
mouth our ancestors in let's say 1,000
ad
100 AD India was the peak of
civilization
globally so prices did did not matter at
the time we were all prosperous so yeah
so that may not quite be the the the
angle along which you would want to
investigate this question but it's a
very good question that mcloven has
asked okay copile says is Rocky the best
movie when it comes to Ultimate
motivation which gives an incredible
message I'm sure you must have watched
it why can't India produce such good
movies of course I watched
Rocky I used to have the DVD I'm sure I
have it somewhere the DVD and I watched
it a lot of
times um look is this the ultimate movie
when it comes to the ultimate motivation
it depends on who you are and what
motivates you for some people it's the
it may be the greatest movie ever you
want get motivated you go and watch
Rocky baloa doing his thing running in
Philly swallowing those raw eggs and
whatnot and the final battle against uh
against Apollo
Creed and yeah great movie overall oh
what Butkus the name of the dog Butkus
is it and and and his coach the guy and
and and his his girlfriend Adrien it's a
great movie no doubt
okay uh certainly uh great under under
under Underdog tail very motivating what
what
motivates you may not motivate somebody
else so I I would say look I I think
it's one of the great movies I really
enjoy
it if you look at it from today's
standards it's kind of a slow movie I've
never had a problem with that but some
people would have you know if you are if
you ask someone from Zen genz today to
watch the movie they'll say oh it's so
slow it's such a slow movie so you know
you'll get get that reaction but it's a
great movie I think I don't really look
at movies for
motivation um some people listen to
motivational speeches some people watch
movies for motivation some people listen
to I of the tiger or some some sort of
music for motivation some people get
motivation from other places it it's up
to you I think it's one of the great
movies I would not say it's one of the
greatest top 10 movies of all time but
it's certainly a great movie and it's a
movie I enjoyed a lot
suddenly mutra says is time travel
possible theoretically it is kind of
possible but uh
practically to achieve that you would
need engineering that is something only
the gods can can can can can can come up
with you would need to have an
engineering project that spans
galaxies okay and then you use
the effect then you would also need to
have a traversable wormhole Einstein
Rosen Bridge we don't know how to keep
the throat of the Wormhole open even if
wormholes do exist we are not sure about
that and to keep the throat of the
Wormhole open to make it a traversable
wormhole you would have to have either
something very exotic like negative Mass
matter which nobody has ever observed or
something even more exotic like a cosmic
string which is a topological defect in
SpaceTime itself that arises that goes
back to the birth of the universe itself
where do we find that how do we harness
that that thing is going to have
ridiculous gravity it's going to warp
everything that comes around it you
don't want to be anywhere near that but
how do you harness that so theoretically
it's possible okay so you if you go from
one one end of the Wormhole to another
and you mod you do certain things then
you may end up at a different time not
just location but time itself
theoretically possible according to
general relativity but practically more
or less impossible unless you are one of
the hyper intelligent alien
uh beings that may or may not exist in
the universe so theoretically it's
possible te technically very almost
impossible to
achieve okay Shari ner says what are
your views on ronata Twitter is divided
about this
should I say no comments that would be
the safe
option what are my views in norn
tataa a trustee of Ford
Foundation undoubtedly it's
known he
funded websites like the
wire significant amount of
funding um Tata instit of soci social
sciences do you know what that is do you
know what sort of a snake pit it is
Marxist snake pit anti-india snake pit H
so um I'd rather not go too much into
this topic is what I what is best okay
my my problem with my dear compatriots
my dear Indians is that you people are
so
clueless you people refuse to indulge
engage in critical thinking it's not
your fault because you have never been
given the luxury of asking questions so
you don't know how to ask questions even
of yourselves the education system
discourages you from asking
questions so you don't ask questions
even after you're out of the education
system you don't know how to ask
questions you don't know how to think
critically everything is in front of
you everything every piece of
information is out there in the public
domain but you will not look at it and
you blindly hero worship
people the problem that we have in India
is that we have no great leaders the
great people who who are worthy of being
Role
Models so we look at so so we worship
fictional characters we worship actors
and actresses we worship Sports people
because at least they are able to
succeed to some extent and we worship
other nations and we put their those
nations flags in our display in our
profiles on on social
media and because and if the media
creates
put somebody up as a on the on a
pedestal as a great person you just hero
worship that person without even looking
into the person's activities which are
available in the public
domain so I will the the the person has
just passed away recently it's best that
I don't speak too much about this but
uh yeah so that's as much as I will say
today okay please do some like they say
do some research do some do some due
diligence you are all able to use the
internet in this technology which means
you are capable of doing
that I know it it's
it's it's hard work to make to do a
Google search I know it's hard work but
please do a little hard work come
on okay myala pendra says what are your
thoughts on Professor sik Raju he upsets
the entire West in mathematicians with
his research I like him straightforward
what do you think of him oh he's a
tremendous
guy you must have seen I think the
podcast that I released recently with
Professor CK Raju tremendous tremendous
intellectual tremendous uh an absolute
poly maath I mean he's done research in
so many different fields computer
science computer programming physics
mathematics time history whatnot an
asset to have we we are lucky to have
somebody like him in the nation he's
obviously getting elderly now but I
think he has many many years ahead of
him and I'm sure he can contribute a
whole lot more to to the world if some
people get
upset by his research well that's their
problem it's not his problem it's not
our problem right so I think he's a gem
of person wonderful wonderful I'm very
fortunate to have met him many times and
spent actual time with him you
know yeah
okay prum Nala says can we ever make
Sanskrit prominent language equivalent
to English and Hindi in India Sanskrit
should be the only civilization language
we should not have Hindi or
English can we do it well not in the
current scenario where our leadership is
blind someday when we will have great
leaders not good leaders but great
leaders it will
happen right
now not going to happen anytime soon
very sad but that's just the case and
I'm not I'm done complaining and whining
about that it's just the way the world
is so be it someday look the true
greatness of India will reemerge someday
we will have great leaders in the future
genuinely great leaders not not goodish
leaders who we think are great okay
genuinely great leaders we have when
when those appear maybe maybe the some
of them are already born who knows
hopefully when that happens
Sanskrit will be revived because it is
the greatest of
languages and it is the only language
that's worthy of being I should be
speaking in Sanskrit and you should all
be able to understand it that's the the
the ideal situation and scenario and it
should be the The Language by which
India is known throughout the world
today they think of India as a language
as a as a nation where you speak Hindi
Hindi is well look I have nothing
against any specific language but Hindi
is nothing compared to Sanskrit Hindi is
an up Branch language it is a kind of a
mongral language a lot of uh lone words
that have crept in from our colonizers
into Hindi tremendous amount of Lone
world and all uh but yeah when you have
mediocre leaders you have mediocrity
that that's that's the currency in the
country you see the the the standards
that you see in a country don't come
from the people they come from the
leadership and the leadership controls
everything
right so even though the people have
high standards but if the leadership
imposes mediocrity mediocre education
mediocre laws mediocre bureaucracy
mediocre everything on
you then what how long will you combat
it eventually you'll get tired you'll
break and you'll just go along with a
thing and after several Generations that
becomes a norm in the country that's
where we are today so it's going to take
time and event actually I'm pretty sure
Sanskrit will reemerge as the only
civilizational language and some people
will be upset with that well I don't
care okay prit mundel says if there's a
war between India and China without any
foreign support then who would win in a
modern conflict I think none will
win neither will
win uh because both are nuclear weapons
powers and if certain lines are cross
then certain horrible things will happen
which will destroy both countries I
don't think it makes sense for India and
China to go to war okay uh I don't think
India and China should go to war I don't
think any sensible leader would think in
that
direction it makes sense for India and
China to find ways to work
together so that's that's how I see it
it's
it's it's disastrous for two nuclear
weapons powers to go to war against each
other
okay Nish Cho says what benefit does the
US get by the influx of immigrants to
Europe you said in the previous podcast
that it's the US doing this changing
demography well you see Europe
historically was the greater power if
you look at the history of the past 500
years Europe was the the
driver of everything in the world the
past 500 years the Europeans colonized
America the Europeans created these
nations in the America South America
North America Etc eventually the us
became independent through its war of
independence and all and they were
always
worried about Europe uh becoming too
powerful in their in the Western
Hemisphere and and in the Americas they
always worried about that they came up
with something called the Monroe
Doctrine which is about keeping the
Europeans away but they were not really
strong enough to enforce that they had
to they had to take the help of the UK
to kind of enforce the Mandu Doctrine in
the 19th century and all the main worry
was Spain for very long time for the US
and so on and in the first half of the
20th century obviously Germany and
Russia became big worries for the
US especially Germany even today I think
they they they are they when you think
when you talk about Germany they can
still see those marching boots and those
Hugo Boss uniforms and they can hear a
seile Victoria Victoria in the
background so that is something that
they still fear so how do you end this
threat once and for all of the the the
possibility that that you may have a
resurgent Germany someday in the future
how do you end that for immigration
obviously see the the the core some one
of the core premises of the third
reik was the the ra the idea of racial
Purity they stole the concept of the ARA
race from us from Indians and they
appropriate the appropriated it they sto
it and they said that the white people
are the true Arians and that the Germans
are the ideal Arian people the superior
Uber mench and so on we are the Supreme
Superior human uh race of the humans and
we should rule the world that sort of
thing that only works when you have
racial Purity right if you have large
scale immigration 20% of of your
nation's population is immigrants of
other other ethnicities and then you
have mixing like what's the term they
use race mixing or whatever and you have
that and you have
a a population that's no longer like
they say racially pure then the whole
idea the whole premise of the third or
whatever
disappears and melts into nothingness
and that's how you ensure that nation is
never a threat in the
future and you can do that to other
nations not just Germany you can do it
to various other nations and and
compromise and Hollow them from
inside you bring in immigrants who are
who who don't respect the host nation's
culture and values and they want to
impose their own foreign culture and
values and they're intolerant
there's Drive there's all kinds of
social tensions and then the Immigrant
Community becomes the dominant community
and they totally destroys the Vitality
health strength Etc of the host nation
and by doing so you can render Europe
entirely
Harless so that's one possible reason
why this may be done Europe was a big
threat for the longest time for the
Americans perhaps it's that or perhaps
I'm entirely wrong and
maybe the Europeans actually want
immigration and they want violent
Invaders to come in and do all kinds of
bad things I don't
know
yeah okay Swati says mahang Balo
arrested okay I wasn't
aware so mahang Balo is this this lady
who is a disident she's of Bal ethnicity
she's a Doctor by
profession and she's one of the
prominent voices
Balo voices that speaking up against
Pakistani occup occupation operation Etc
in balistan the forced disappearances of
people and all the brutal atrocities
that the
Pakistani uh regime the the Army the
military is is perpetrating on the
people of balistan so she is a prominent
voice so okay I wasn't aware I don't
like I said I don't really follow what's
happening in Pakistan too much I'm not
interested that much so she has been
arrested the Pak the pashon movement has
been banned PTM PTI Pakistan insa is
Imran Khan's party they are protesting
TTP Taliban Pakistan B bistan Liberation
Army Tribal wars inber pakon Kashmir is
unhappy Shia Sunni issues IMF loans your
views please are things bad are things
things worse for Pakistan look like I've
always said I was not aware of the
arrest of marang Bach but okay that's
news for me
as I've said there are so many factors
and forces within
Pakistan that seek
to be free from the the heavy boot the
oppressive Bo of the Pakistani military
there are so many forces within Pakistan
that seek to break Pakistan apart just
naturally
spontaneously it's it's external forces
that have kept Pakistan unified thus far
because Pakistan has a certain kind of
utility geopolitically for them Vis A
India Vis Iran Vis Afghanistan Vis the
overall area etc for a certain kind of
geopolitical Power Balance okay and
especially as a counterbalance to India
as a nuisance Factor Visa India to India
to keep India off balance at all
whenever
required so things are bad for Pakistan
things have always been bad for Pakistan
Pakistan is always Two Steps From Hell
Two Steps From collapse Two Steps from
being a failed state but it's never
allowed to become a failed State it's
never allowed to to collapse because it
has utility for The Who for whoever owns
Pakistan right now
whoever whoever pays the bills of the
Pakistani military who whoever is
putting money in their pockets right now
it's the
Americans so yeah there are all these
issues IMF loans Pakistan is forever in
debt and they'll be allowed to exist as
long as they are of utility so all these
issues the balistan issue the kber pakun
issue Sun issues like you said Kashmir
are deeply unhappy now in Pakistan they
would like to reunite with
India uh Tribal Wars wars
inak PTI democracy has been stifled
there was a coup Imran Khan has been
jailed for for I don't know three two
three
years uh all that so things are bad
things have always been bad for Pakistan
the past 20 30 years
okay but yeah it's going to keep on
existing it's going to keep on limping
for forward the Pakistani military is
going to keep going to keep on getting
money from wherever it's getting money
and they're going to keep on serving
that mercenary agenda so there you have
there you have
it okay Bangladesh we haven't spoken
about Bangladesh today thus far uh onil
abtahi says what do I think about the
Bangladesh situation
terrible so Bangladesh is now as we know
there's been a coup in Bangladesh shik
has been Ed and a new puppet regime is
is now installed in Bangladesh Mohammad
yunus is a US puppet we know that very
well okay he recently went to the US and
count out to his Masters and brought out
then made Revelations that make it very
clear that this was a very meticulously
planned operation the whole
coup and uh met with his Masters and so
on and overall that's what it is so we
have East Pakistan now and West Pakistan
once again that's the
situation we have two reasonably hostile
neighbors Pakistan is a fully hostile
Bangladesh also now becomes a hostile
power for
India uh they're making real rather
annoying statements the Bangladesh is
aren't they just to annoy
India
and beside that beyond that we have a
horrible situation in Bangladesh for the
Bangladeshi
Hindus they are being targeted every day
some new horror story comes out involved
civilians women girls Hindus Hindu
temples Hindus are under attack in
Bangladesh um and that's the situation
so it's it's bad it's bad things are
getting worse in Bangladesh if you a
Hindu that's what I think and and things
aren't going to change anytime soon this
is a newly newly installed puppet
government a newly installed Bangladesh
is a newly newly minted US vasal
state um
so the situation is bad it is sad to say
that shik was doing good work you I
don't care what people say about her
that she was undemocratic dictatorial
whatever she did a great job with the
Bangladeshi economy she improved
relations to a significant extent great
extent with India the whole region the
Bengal
region that whole region became more
stable she cracked down on terrorist
activities within our nation or it was
good now you're going to have chaos
Bangladesh will go down the same road as
Pakistan so overall it's it's it's
bad
okay aush Pandi says the West always
vilifies Russian weapons but actual case
in Battleground Russia seems to be a
beast look they destroyed mq9 Reaper
drone with suo 27 made in the
1980s it always makes sense to vilify
your opponents and their military
capabilities this is called
psychological
warfare propaganda Warfare when I was a
kid in the
80s you always I live in the West West
okay a Western Country European country
and it the Russians were Pro were
portrayed as the masters of propaganda
everything the Russians do and say is
propaganda propaganda propaganda it
turns out the West is the master of
propaganda okay they they take it to a
whole different level and they own the
means of production of news and memes
mems whatever and they use it to excuse
me to uh to
tremendous tremendous amount
of
success so um I think Russian weapons
are reasonably good see the mq9 Reaper
drone is a subsonic drone that doesn't
have anti fighter plane capabilities
anti missile capabilities so if you have
a suo 27 made in the 80s and you launch
a missile that when the missile locks on
the Drone there's nothing much the Drone
can do about it I'm not sure if it has
it can chaff or flares or
whatever so um Russian weapons are
robust they may not be the highest the
most high-tech weapons but they are
robust some of their helicopters are
built like tanks some of their airplanes
are built like tanks and so on so I
think Russian weapons are reasonably
good you cannot underestimate Russian
weapons and of course it's good that we
Indians we have weapons a source from
Russia so it's good for us
overall
okay
[Music]
um Kar says are North Korea and South
Korea going to war is Russia involved
why would they go to war there's nothing
happening in the world right now that
suggests anything of the sort right now
right is there any T are there any
tensions in the Korean Peninsula right
now not that I've heard of
um are there any provocative statements
made by either side I not that I've
heard of so there is nothing that
indicates that either Nation or both
Nations will be going to war I don't see
any of that happening so my answer is
doesn't look like
that
um blazy says would it have been better
if India's population would have been
around 400 to 500 million so go back to
1947 undivided India's population was
about 300 or 300 in the in the vicin of
300 million undivided India included
Pakistan and east and west
Pakistan right I'm not counting Burma
because Burma was partitioned in 1935 or
thereabouts but in 1947 the population
of undivided India was about 300 million
that's the right kind of population for
Nation the size of undivided India so
divided India's population would have
the ideal population is around let's say
250 to 300
million in the
1980s which is not a whole lot of time
ago India's population was about 600
million less than half of what it is
today okay so the population growth has
been a disaster for India but that
doesn't mean that we should seek to have
a one child policy and as fast as
possible bring the population down that
will be a disaster which will end
India now the right solution is to
gradually bring the population down over
a period of 100 or 200 years okay you
have to do the math to understand why it
is so because if you have a rapidly
declining population you're going to end
up with a very old population the median
age will be in the 60s and 70s do you
want a population where the average
person is 60 years old it's a disaster
for the country
so the ideal population for a country
like India is around 300
million but it doesn't mean that we do
anything drastic it's going to be a 100
or 200 year project to bring it down
gradually to around 300 million that's
the optimum population imagine if you
have only 300 million people in India
today it's 1,400 million right 1.4
billion almost five times 300 million if
you had only 300 million people in India
imagine what the roads will look like
what the traffic will look like there'll
be no traffic
jams you have some cities in India like
Mumbai Etc where you have horribly
congested trains people get packed into
trains you won't have that you won't
have all those jams in airports the
whole country will look different it'll
be much more pleasant country we just
overpopulated but there's no immediate
solution for that we're going to have to
be
patient really patient
and wait for a couple of centuries for
the population to slowly come down to
300 but right now the Indian TFR is
dropping total fertility rate it's
around two for a sustained population at
the same level you need a TFR of
2.1 in some states it's 1.7 1.6 bad
signs we don't want population collapse
in India it'll be disaster we already
seen that in China we already seen that
in Japan we've seen that in various
Western Nations European nations we
don't want that here
but so the government will have to be
extra vigilant and take the right steps
I'm not sure if they're doing or not
doing it but that's what I can
say Okay Shri Watsa says it's a question
about physics theoretical physics if
virtual particle pairs are equal in Mass
how does a black hole lose Mass if one
Falls in how does the escaping particle
get enough energy to escape the clutches
of extreme gravity okay I'm going to
give you a scenario
completely theoretical scenario and not
entirely accurate that this this is how
it happens but imagine this situation
okay it's not entirely accurate but it's
a good analogy to give you to kind of
understand how it happens you have a
black hole okay whatever size it is a
black hole of mass m it has a horizon
which is called The Event Horizon that
is the boundary of no return so here is
the black hole center here is the black
hole and if you cross the Event Horizon
then you will never return so let's say
you are right at the boundary of the
boundary of no
return and because of the incredible
gravity gravitational strength of a
black
hole or not because of it just just
randomly a virtual particle antiparticle
pair is formed see space isn't empty
Quantum field Theory tells us space
isn't empty it's steaming with these
virtu virtual particle antiparticle
pairs that don't quite break the laws of
physics they obey Heisenberg's
uncertainty
principle the
time version not the energy version the
time version so you have a particle
antiparticle pair that is formed
spontaneously it's going to collapse
again and nothing will be changed in the
universe but this particle anti particle
pair it has been formed because of the
gravity of the black hole so the bill
the energy bill
of the formation of the particle
antiparticle Fair pair is footed by the
black hole okay so some of the black
holes energy mass energy is converted
into a particle anti particle pair which
in regular circumstances would would
once again merge together and nothing
will happen and the black hole loses
nothing but because this happened at the
Event
Horizon one one particle goes into the
black hole and another one escapes so
this virtual particle antiparticle pair
became becomes a real particle
antiparticle pair because one is lost
inside the black hole and one goes
outside and because the the mass energy
bill was footed by the black hole the
black hole rings in
Mass that's what happens that's kind of
how you can see it it's it's a very
rough and rather imprecise
analogy but that's how it happens that's
that's how we can think of it happening
so it's it's a
the the particle pairs are obviously the
both the particles are equal in Mass but
they have opposite signs right particle
anti particle opposite quantum numbers
so that's how the black hole loses Mass
when one Falls in it would not lose Mass
if both fell in but one
escapes and that mass was actually the
mass of the black hole so that's what
happens right and and that's that's the
phenomenon of Hawking
radiation the black holes appear to
radiate radiation coming out
and the radiation exhibits a black body
Spectrum completely
random so that's how a black hole seems
to have temperature and radiation and
that's how it loses Mass black hole
evaporation Hawking evaporation Hawking
temperature and Hawking radiation that's
how it happens all
right
okay
um okay cool gamer says do there exist
different uncertainty principles in
Universe apart from heisenbergs have you
ever observed another phenomena where
it's impossible to measure two
quantities simultanously not that I can
think of off the top of my head there is
only the quantum in when it comes to the
quantum world there's only one un
uncertainty principle which is
Heisenberg's uncertainty
principle and uh yeah that kind of
imposes a limit onto the Precision of
our
measurements uh there's no other
uncertainty principle that I aware of
aush Pand says the SEO 527 dumped fuel
on mq9 Ripper drone and crashed it yeah
I remember seeing that video how does
fuel crash a drone but that's what it
seemed to be like I I do remember that
video that's in the beginning of the war
right in the near the Crimea
region uh the death Hunter says do you
see Bangladesh splitting up in the
future where Modi steps in to end the
atrocities against minorities um I would
say let Mr Modi first step in and end
atrocities against minority against
Hindus in
India I don't see Mr Modi stepping in
when it comes to
Bangladesh I don't see that
happening um it doesn't mean that Mr
Modi is weak or India is weak or
anything it's just the way it is India
is a non-interventionist power
India India doesn't intervene so the
minority is in Bangladesh have been left
to their own devices whatever happens
will happen not India's problem
Bangladesh is a separate nation right
that's that's how the government of
India deals with things so U I would be
extraordinary surprise extraordinarily
surprised in a pleasant way if Mr Modi
actually intervenes I don't see that
happening and even if uh so if if that
doesn't happen then how does Bangladesh
split
up so yeah I don't see that happening
unfortunately okay Manan panal says if
communism is that bad how did the Soviet
Union Soviet Empire remain so successful
despite following that ideology uh dear
friend Dear Sir the Soviet Empire broke
up it
disintegrated
yes and why did it disintegrate so many
factors that caused this it's not one
factor that caused it
So Many Factors call it one of the
factors was decline in standards over
time over time more and more decline in
standards because of what
communism
everything the Soviets initially had
extremely good
supercomputers if you go back to the
extremely good computers and
supercomputers you go back to the 50s
you have that situation by the 1960s the
Soviets were like two or three years
behind the US
in Computing by the 70s the Soviets were
five six seven years behind the US by
the 80s the Soviets were at least a
decade behind the US slowly gradually de
declining
standards in Computing and in every
other
thing okay there were all kinds of
limitations and restrictions imposed on
the citizens of the USSR which would not
have in the
west there was Collective
collectivization as we know and so on so
communism to a large extent contributed
to a lot of the various
factors that are all exhibitions of
declining standards that eventually
caused the caused the collapse of the
USSR communism is bad the Soviet Union
is an example of how communism is
bad so please understand see you seem to
have and I don't blame you for this you
seem to have the impression that
communism is what contributed to the
existence of the USSR for a certain
amount of time but it broke up it
collapsed it was a
disaster you you have to study history
to understand this how much of a
disaster it was for the people of the
USSR they lost
everything all their wealth was held
collectively in the coffers of the USSR
after the collapse of the USSR all that
wealth was distributed to a number of
oligarch
who destroyed the wealth who ruined the
U who ruined Russia that's why Russia
you had cues for soup in the
1990s all the wealth all the savings of
the people of the USSR over seven or
whatever number of
decades were thrown down the
drain this happened because of the
collapse the collapse happened because
of Communism and its declining standards
so
we are not taught any of this so I don't
blame people for having these ideas and
opinions but you have to educate
yourself if this is something that
interests you please read upon this many
good books about this and many books
don't speak about this but you have to
educate yourself to understand that it's
communism to a very large extent that
caused
this all right
um vishak n says what are your
predictions on the upcoming US elections
what are its effects on
India
um you know excuse me right now you will
notice that the Americans uh the US
government the us as a nation is kind of
going after India it's arm twisting
India in a lot of ways it's rather harsh
and hostile towards India in so many
different ways you can see signs and
symptoms of this all over the place the
kind of EDS that Publications put out
regarding India the kind of uh Think
Tank articles that come out the coup in
Bangladesh that is an anti-india coup
the coup in Pakistan also do you know
there was a k Pakistan in 2022 Imran
Khan's
ster and and so much more a tremendous
amount of hostility towards
India so when did this all begin when
did things start going bad between India
and the USA it was 2019
2020 2020 onwards what happened in
2020 Trump lost and whoever Biden Biden
won the Democrats came to power and the
Democrats have historically been way
more anti-india than the
Republicans okay so it does affect
India to a certain extent at least when
Trump was in power he was rather warm
towards India he had his own way of
dealing with things
but the situation wasn't
bad so what do I think is going to
happen in the US elections look I am not
a theologist I am not some election
expert
whatever I I look at geopolitics I look
at
how how a nation is
run uh
and whoever runs the US clearly it's not
Joe Biden or Kamala Harris somebody is
running the US whatever you want to call
it the blob the Deep State The
Establishment whatever right um they see
Trump as an
outsider they see 2016 which is Trump's
Victory as a big
mistake and in 2020 they rectified the
mistake and ensure that Trump does not
win by hook or by they ensured it okay
let's keep it at
that
and right now it does appear that Trump
is the more popular among the two
candidates it's Trump versus Kamala
Harris right Kamala is doesn't seem to
be as popular as Trump even if if you
look at the various uh po the ratings
and whatnot I think Trump's leading
right at least some of them show that
Trump is leading so overall it would
look like Trump should probably win but
I think it's difficult for that to
happen I think it's unlikely that Trump
will win
unless unless Trump has kissed the ring
and D done some kind of back room deal
with the powers that
be uh so overall I think it's it's uh
unlikely that Trump will win unlik
unless he has kissed the ring is it
possible that he may have kissed the
ring it's
possible well in that case things won't
change much even if he comes to power
you can see that lots of prominent
people are supporting Trump you can see
Elon Musk is
all in on Trump he's Tak his
whole well he's he's officially endorsed
Trump and he
doesn't waste an opportunity to to
promote Trump and and support his
campaign he even appeared on one of his
election rallies right Elon mus jumped
around and all
that uh so all that does
matter uh but I still think it's
difficult for Trump to win I think
Kamala Harris may be the next president
I I would be much more happy to see
Trump win because first of all he's very
entertaining okay it makes the world a
more interesting place and probably he's
better for the
US the US used to be a great
country it was something that everybody
looked up to the US is still the most
important nation in the world the most
powerful nation in the world and if that
is the most important powerful Nation it
it's it's good if it's a nation with
high standards not a nation in
Decline so I think overall Trump will be
better for the US than Kamala Harris but
who am I to say say all that I an
outsider the people of the US will
decide what
happens if they actually are the ones
who
decide uh Trump says that 2020 was
stolen a stolen election which means a
rigged election so there are very
serious allegations out there so all of
that is the context in which we are
making we are having this
discussion I think it's difficult for
Trump to win I think they'll ensure he
doesn't win unless he has made some kind
of secret agreement with the powers that
b in which case whether Trump wins or
Kamala wins you won't see much of a
difference in US foreign policy and all
that maybe if Trump wins it'll be
slightly better for India if Kamala wins
oh it's going to get worse for India so
that's how I see it I can't really make
predictions but I think it's difficult
for Trump to win it's it's less likely
that Trump will win I'll be happy to be
proven wrong
okay Brides says will the US election be
cancelled if the US goes to war with
China before elections
no even if the US goes to war with China
it's it's China is nothing compared to
the US the US is way too powerful for
China just think about it we haven't
used the map too much today think about
it okay this is China here we're looking
at China and you have the small island
of the coast of of China called Taiwan
it is right in China's backyard the US
is so powerful China can't even take
this island which is right off its
Coast that is how powerful the US
is China is no match for the us if the
US and China go to war CH the US can
squash China like a
bug no offense to the to the Chinese I
have a great amount of respect for China
for everything they've achieved but they
are no match for the US the us is just
way too powerful the US is the most
powerful today as the as it has ever
been so um I don't see the US and China
going to war China is not stupid they do
want to continue existing don't they so
such a scenario won't won't
happen okay let's see some
um other
interesting okay J manraj Singh say says
please revive the Indian interest
podcast I'm going to start something new
next
month it won't be the Indian interest
but I I hope it's going to be something
that will be of interest to you it's
going to be a big project big
project starting
soon my opinion about iPhone Factory in
Tamil Nadu CAU fire shouldn't we step
our step up our safety standards to
avoid such incidents as it affects
future Investments so I haven't really
looked into
this in any detail but it's unfortunate
this thing happened it sends a bad
signal to the investors who want to
invest in the country and those who have
already invested we have to take care of
the the foreign companies that invest in
India um so I'm not sure what what was
the cause of this but it sends a bad
signal that's my opinion about this we
should ensure such incidents do not
happen ah finally somebody talks about
this a way says recently the US UK has
agreed to hand over sovereignty of the
long contested chos
Islands to macius you didn't mention
macius here sir okay so the islands the
chos islands the sovereignty is going to
go to
macius will it include dieo Garcia yes
it will include Diego Garcia what are My
Views about this My Views about this is
that it's a
joke it's just in namesake it's it's
it's a nam namesake thing the UK will
still continue to own and operate Diego
Garcia technically the sovereignty will
reside with
macius technically but in the real world
nothing will change in the UK I think
they will take the island on Le or
something for 99 or so years to begin
with so nothing
changes the UK still will continue to
operate and control Diego Garcia and the
UK also isn't only in
namesake it's only name it's actually
the US that's controlling and operating
Diego Garcia nothing
changes and you know
what go to the
map see this is where chos is
okay compared to where India is now this
is an island it's it's a Naval Base Air
Force Base that allows the US to project
tremendous amount of power in this
region and it's not such a bad for India
because it kind of keeps China away so
overall it's okay for India it's it's
a so so that's how I see it it's not
really much of a change technically the
sovereignty goes back to macius but in
the real world scenario nothing changes
Diego Garcia Still Remains with the US
and overall it's it's not so bad for
India so there you have it nothing
really changes but on paper things
change like on paper today
uh article 370 has been removed from
Jammu and Kashmir on paper but on the
ground has anything changed have the
Kashmir pandits uh been allowed to to go
back to to to Jammu and Kashmir the
Kashmir Valley nothing has changed so
the change has happened on paper not in
the real world not on the ground
similarly this Doo Garcia thing chos
sovereignty Chang has happened on paper
nothing has changed on the ground there
you have it
Grim soad says Manipur action when Modi
attended asan Summit something cooking
something has been cooking or something
or the other has been cooking forever
Manipur action
when I have no
idea uh I don't see any point about
Manipur Manipur action when I have no
idea Manipur is a
disaster that's what I will say Manipur
is a disaster
skand Gupta says why does India always
punch below her weight geopolitically
inactive when tiny Nations like France
Israel UK even Iran punch above their
weight and always active is it due to
lack of political will or lack of
capacity what is political will it's the
will of the leader
right when when Modi came to power in
2014 the whole world was watching India
what is this guy going to do right
because everybody knows what a nation
the size of India can actually do if it
chooses to do something it can shake up
the whole
world but now look at India where are we
we do nothing we can do a regim change
right in our backyard India will do
nothing you can unleash Mayhem genocide
on Hindus in Bangladesh India will do
nothing look the other
way so it's about
leadership it's about leadership
leadership leadership your your name is
scand Gupta scand Gupta the H hun
Slayer if scand Gupta was in charge of
India today you think India would behave
the same
way it would be a whole different
India one of our greatest
Emperors his
entire career was an extended military
campaign and he was a good man he made
India a much better
place
so it's all about
leadership um we haven't had great
leaders the we haven't been fortunate
enough to see the emergence of great
leaders the past few hundred years the
last great leader I can think of was
chhatrapati shivaji
Maharaj before him one can think of
rajendra Chola and his dad Raj Raj Chola
right uh we had a few good leaders
during the freedom struggle people like
naaji subash Chandra BOS but what
happened we know what happened right
couldn't do much
unfortunately so uh it is circumstances
also that
Define a
leader you may be a great leader with a
tremendous amount of ability but you are
in charge of a small nation and you have
enemies that are too powerful you may
not be able to do anything or you may
end up being like chinis Khan who
destroys all his enemies so at the end
of the day it's all about leadership the
performance of a
nation is
entirely
um due to the kind of leadership it has
we haven't had great leaders for a very
long
time and I I said earlier right we in
India the people of India are
starved of
greatness there's not a single role
model on the horizon who exudes true
greatness there's just mediocrity around
right that's why Indians worship other
nations you see so many Indians putting
Israeli Flags on their on their profile
on social media why because they admire
Israel Israel does what India doesn't
dare to do it's not because India isn't
strong or India is not great it's
because our leadership isn't
great right leadership matters
leadership is what makes or breaks a
nation so if India is always punching
below its weight if India is always
geopolitically inactive and so on I
think you should take a look at what
your leaders are doing what is the
quality of the leaders that you have and
have had in the
past
okay Su that says any selfhelp book
suggestions uh I I don't self-help I
would rather refrain from giving
self-help book ex suggestions I have
read my share of self-help books has any
of them helped me really
not
much uh so I don't
know I can't think of any of the top of
my
head um if I can think of some some good
books selfhelp books then I'll I'll let
you know in the future but right now I
can't think of any sorry about that
sorry
apologies um
Kip says recently six languages got the
status of classical language including
asames Bangla Etc what's my take on this
you know this classical and Quantum
debate classical versus Quant okay
that's physics right classical you know
there what what's the definition of
classical language what's the
definition what's the definition of a
classical dance versus a Quantum dance
or or a non-classical dance
why do we need to have this terminology
and this
this this thing of attaching a certain
kind of diagonal
language I I don't get it make every
language a classical language Asam is I
mean look how old is as is is a
language not quite sure it's it's one of
the newer uper Branch languages newer in
the context of 10,000 years of Indian
civilization right I would say if you
want to call something classical it has
to have a certain set of criteria that
you it it it
meets the first Criterion I would say is
a language should be at least 2,000
years old to be a classical
language do these languages meet those
criteria I don't think so only Sanskrit
and Tamil meet those criteria Telugu
also I'm sure Telugu is probably older
than Tamil
um so from that Viewpoint only two or
three languages can be Classical
Languages and obviously these languages
if you want to call them classical anges
need to have a tremendous amount of
literature a huge Corpus of
literature now from that perspective do
so I don't know on what basis they've
given the title of classical language I
don't know what's the purpose of doing
this I think it's got some kind of
political purpose if you truly value
your languages then why don't you do
something to promote them instead of
putting a tag on them classical
language India India's leaders are all
words no action all words all slogans no
action if you want to promote
ases why don't you give 2,000
Scholarships in India fiveyear
scholarships to genuine Scholars who
will produce new literature in ases you
can do that
no but you won't vote so you will say
Assam is a is a classical language and
banga is a classical language but maybe
dogre is a Quantum language
right and
this is just I
mean what's my take on this I think this
is all nonsense I think every language
is important every Indian language is
important and if the government truly
values India's culture and language they
will put their money where their mouth
is not just put put tags on languages to
to hopefully get some votes very very I
don't know
Annoying every language should be valued
every language should be promoted the
government should invest money in the
promotion of every
language give scholarships to Scholars
and writers and authors who can create
new literature in Indian
languages right you're going to have to
spend money for that but will the
government do that no no no
no so yeah it's it's just it's a farce
it's a joke it will make a lot of people
happy Indians St Indians Chas status
right oh my language is now a classical
language what difference does it make in
your
life what difference does it make to
your language are you going to have more
output of literature in your language
now is your language going to last
longer now because it's now got the tag
of a classical language it makes no
difference in the real
world uh so when it comes to culture
this government is a horrible
non-performer I'm talking about the
Narendra Modi government extremely poor
performer in terms of culture they've
done nothing for Indian culture the done
a great deal for India's infrastructure
for India's economy when it comes to
culture they've done nothing and that is
extremely
disappointing
okay
um Sharma says was Tibet ever a part of
India it was never part of India but
it's part of the indosphere okay it's
it's part of India's extended extended
uh sphere of culture and influence Tibet
culturally is Indian it's got a very
different take on Indian culture a very
different manifestation of Indian
culture but it is Indian culture through
and
through so Tibet should have been part
should should be part of the indosphere
we should have protected Tibet in the
1950s we did not our government
was well you know what it was wasn't
it but historically Tibet has never been
administered by any Indian Emperor King
Empire some parts at some points may
have been of course we know that but the
whole of Tibet no so Tibet historically
has not been part of India it's always
been in our sphere of influence Tibet is
Tibetan culture is more or less Indian
culture in a very different form and
they are our
civilizational brothers and sisters the
Tibetans there are people ethnically
they may be different for most Indians
the how does it matter how many times
have I said this DNA doesn't matter
culture matters so culturally Tibet is
Indian
but geopolitically or or from that
perspective politically it was never a
part of India and so what that's fine
but we never had borders and all that
with Tibet Kash Manser over that's in
Tibet isn't it that's one of our holiest
pilgrimage sites and did Indians ever
need visas and passports to go there
never it's only now after Tibet came
under Chinese occupation that that's
that's
happened so yeah that's your answer
sir
okay the Knight says how do Indians deal
with Rising racism in online in real
life look as your country becomes more
relevant relevant and it starts making
its own Pres felt in the global stage
geopolitically and not as a pushover not
as an apologetic country but as a
country that stands up straight you're
going to face this okay so you're going
to face this online you're going to face
this in real life also perhaps in some
places how do you deal with it you deal
with it you you be assertive you stand
up for yourself you you if you are in a
foreign country and you're facing and
you let's say you face racism you got to
stand up straight you stand up for
yourself you don't intelligent violence
but you don't take it and you don't
respond by being racist in turn you not
you just uh you've got to be assertive
and you need to know how
to how to handle
that and uh you Indians when the travel
they will probably face racism in some
countries more than other
countries um so it's going to happen and
that's just some that's what we call
Growing Pains okay so you got to be
mentally prepared for it first of all
and secondly you need to be mentally
prepared for how you're going to respond
to such a situation if it arises right
so racism can take so many different
forms and depending on the context you
deal with it in different ways so the
first thing you to do is to be mentally
prepared you to know what racism is if
you're going out for the first time or
if you're going online for the first
time you need to know what racism
is and racism is different online racism
is different in real life life it's
sometimes more subtle in real life
sometimes it's more in your face in real
life online it's just blatant it's it's
just non-stop you just ignore it who
cares right um so first of all you need
to acknowledge that racism exists you
need to know what racism is you need to
know what are the signs and symptoms of
racism you need to know how to handle
that all of that you have to do do you
to prepare yourself mentally for it and
that's how you deal with it but it's
going to be there and it's going to it's
going to rise it's going to
increase
okay okay let's talk about aliens X xmus
Yus zus what are my views on UFO UAP
topic if they release 4K videos want
that create chaos in the west like War
of the Worlds sanis will be chilling
with mint julips with Mahadev in heart
okay I don't know what that last portion
is and what does it have to do with UFOs
and uaps UFOs is United
not United unidentified flying objects
UAP is unidentified aial
phenomena uh what's my opinion on this
it looks like it exists look like looks
like it exists only in the west only in
the US more or less you don't see too
much of that in India for example or
China or or or Asia see a lot of that in
the US which kind of raises certain
questions either the aliens only like
the us as a place to visit or it's not
aliens but it's actually classified to
technology maybe it is lo heed Martin
technology maybe it's boing technology
if it doesn't
crash okay maybe they have uh achieved
certain technological breakthroughs that
allow them
to test such aircraft spacecraft
whatever so um that's what I think I
think look I I've said this so many
times regular viewers will know this
that emerging Technologies new
technologies they typically are first
made a available to militaries and they
are kept hidden secret for decades
before some
some percentage of the technology is
released to the in the public domain
just a little bit so if you have a
certain amount of AI capabilities that
are visible in the public eye you can be
sure that the US military will have an
AI That's at least 100 times more
powerful than what you have access
to and
similarly and so on so most likely if
these UFOs uaps are actual genuine
phenomena then it most likely represents
a classified technology that is being
tested or deployed by the American
Military that's what I think it
is and that's why 4K footage will not be
released okay let's take a few more
questions
um annabe jaon says where do you think
the real power lies in India as you
mentioned that democracies in
democracies the yeah when you have a
democracy that often hides where the
real power
resides so where does the real power lie
in India in in India the real power is
is distributed and it's
diffused it's not in one single
place so if you go back two and a half
thousand years most of the power when
you had the Moria Empire the beginning
of the Moria Empire that time in India
most of the power lay with Chandra Gupta
Moria the Emperor of
India a couple of generations later most
of the power in the
subcontinent lay in the hands of Ashok
Moria okay and
he controlled the whole
subcontinent his one word could change
the the fate of a whole region depending
on whatever policy or whatever pron M he
made that was concentration of power
when you have a subcontinent sized
Nation you need that sort of thing in
today's India where does power lie a
little bit of power lies in the hands of
the Prime Minister and the central
government a significantly more power
lies if you're living in any City or
Village a lot more power lies in your
state
government
right in your district magistrate in the
hands of your District M magistrate in
the police forces the bureaucracy the
judici
so in India the power is distributed you
have a federal
system you have a very powerful
bureaucracy you have a very powerful
Judiciary and so
on
um so that's how it is India is a very
decentralized kind of country and that's
why you can't have a coup in India on
the one hand it's good on the other hand
it's terrible because you have such a
weak central government right the
central government take can take care of
Economic Policy foreign policy defense
policy beyond that everything else is
the domain of the Dominion of the state
governments and they decide what happens
and the central government can't do too
much about about it unless it's a
national security issue and even the
case of National Security issues like
illegal immigration the central
government seems to be doing nothing
about things in certain states without
naming those
States so in India the real power lies
all around the place it's all
distributed it's not the way things
should
be a Nation the size of India you need
to have a very strong central government
only then can things happen in India
quickly in today's world the faster a
nation the the the smaller is the time
gap between a decision that is taken and
action is done as soon if if the if the
delay is small then the nation will do
better the more agile Nation Nation you
are the more agile a nation you are the
the more you will succeed in the 21st
century in India
agility forget about agility inertia so
in India the power is
distributed lots of politicians have
small small amounts of power in every
city in every village in every
District lots of Institutions not lots a
small number of Institutions have a lot
of power they can stand up to the state
to the central government if they wish
to they can arm twist the central
government and have elections conducted
in some state if they want to so the
central government is in in in a nation
like India the way it is structured it's
extremely
weak very weak so India doesn't have a
deep State like the US has the US has a
very very powerful very centralized deep
State all the real power lies there all
the real power lies there in India all
distributed that's why it's a nation
that's that's always at odds with itself
various parts of the nation are trying
to pull the nation in different
directions and the end result is that
nothing happens and the nation goes
nowhere so it's it's because of the way
the nation was created the the it was
constructed the Constitution and the
laws and the structure and all that the
governance of structure all that it's
it's designed to keep in India
perpetually immobile in a state of
constant
inertia and that's why India has never
been able to become a good Nation rather
than a great nation India is capable of
incredible greatness but it's been
designed the system has been designed to
ensure India never becomes
great there you have it
anabeth
okay
uh Vikram says why doesn't have doesn't
India have Aviation companies like
Boeing Airbus Bombardier loid Martin
those are all private companies in the
in the US uh momad was in the US right
but loin Martin arabus arabus is is
European and so
on these are private companies in India
can a private
company uh start designing and and
creating aircraft you need a lot of
capital for that a lot of money and for
the longest time private Enterprise was
was stifled in India and even today it's
it's so hard to do business in India
whether you're a smalltime entrepreneur
whether you're a medium business whether
big business all kinds of problems you
know India isn't the nicest place for
doing business uh so lots of problems
right I wish you had these company
companies like these in India would have
been great I wish there was a company or
multiple companies like SpaceX in India
but we don't have it the government has
to create the right atmosphere the right
environment for such companies to emerge
and take off so we have one private
Aerospace startup of some kind I forget
the name that's come up and that's
launched a couple of solid state Rockets
all good good Beginnings but why don't
we have 30 of
those so U the government's job is to
create the right kind of environment for
such companies to emerge and then Thrive
and compete with each other and Excel
and because we don't don't have that
environment that's why India doesn't
have such Aviation companies the longest
time private Enterprise was crushed now
it's not crushed but but things need to
be made way
better so that's
why okay let's take one final question
for today for
today
uh let us see let us see let us see what
other can I take one question okay let's
okay let's take one question from
geopolitical dub does hypnosis work how
strong can it be hypnosis
Works hypnosis is uh when you
communicate or somebody communicates and
reaches out to your subconscious mind so
there are you know what if you know
psychology you have a conscious mind and
a subconscious mind and the conscious
mind is something that you have to
struggle against the subconscious mind
is something you can train and so on the
conscious mind is about 5% of who you
are and the subconscious mind maybe
about 90 95% of you are who you are and
hypnosis is all about tapping into the
subconscious mind and making suggestions
and perhaps uh making changes in the
person's uh psyche behavior and all that
and there is something called
autohypnosis wherein you can hyp wherein
you hypnotize yourself with your with
your eyes open it's possible so hypnosis
does work it can be really strong it can
be really powerful depending on
the subject the person who is doing it
whether you're doing it to yourself
whether you're having somebody else
doing doing it to you and how skilled
that person is hypnosis is indeed
something that exists it certainly does
work and I would know because because I
know okay all right all right okay we
done with today's
episode Ailes is already saying good
night so yes thank you very much good
day good night to all of you thank you
so much for all the questions and I will
see you in the episode or episodes that
come up next week next week we going to
have episodes and I look forward to
taking your questions then so it's been
a break for for me last week or so but
I'm back now and we're going to continue
so thank you so much for your
questions keep asking questions keep
raising your standards and I will see
you very soon thank you so much good day
good night bye